早上好啊 执政官
Morning, Consul.
今天过得怎么样
How goes your day?
站住
Stop!
我为你深感骄傲
I am so proud of you.
我们的名声已经洗清 共和国现在安全了
Our name is redeemed. The Republic is safe.
太可怕了 母亲
It was horrible, mother.
他不愿意死
He wouldn't die.
但是他已经死了 现在死了
But he is dead now, eh?
他本来还想跟我说话
He tried to speak to me.
可是发不出声音
But no words came out.
我们现在要坚强些
We must be strong now.
是啊
Yes.
元老院会来寻求我们的指引
The senate will look to us for leadership.
人民需要坚定有力的手
The people will need a firm hand.
对吗
hm?
你能够承担这个责任吗
Are you up to the task?
主啊
Dominus.
你是谁 你是谁的孩子
Who are you? Whose child is this?
你都干了什么 放开他 放开他
What did you do? Let him go, let him go!
不 不 不要
No, no, don't!
发发慈悲吧
Please have mercy.
我诅咒你 我诅咒你
I curse you. Curse you.
我诅咒你们所有人
I curse you all!
以冥土众神之名起誓
By all the gods below.
我诅咒你们直至毁灭
I curse you to damnation.
凯撒死了 凯撒死了
Caesar is dead! Caesar is dead!
他死了 他已经死了
He's dead! He's dead!
凯撒已经死了
Caesar is dead!
丢下它 别管了
Leave it, forget it.
你听到我说的话了
You heard what I said!
母亲
Mother?
让我一个人待着
Leave me alone.
天啊 不会连你也是吧 哭哭啼啼一点用处也没有
Gods, not you as well? Crying will not help us.
我没哭 我是愤怒
I'm not crying. I'm angry.
真希望冥神活吃了那头叫赛维莉娅的母猪
May Dis devour that bitch pig Servilia.
我真是个傻瓜
What a fool I was.
如果我没有把乌瑞纳斯和他妻子的事告诉她
If I'd not told her of Vorenus and his wife...
听我说 我们决不能承认自己卷入了这件事
Listen to me. We must never speak of our part in this.
人家会把我们当共犯的
It may be mistaken for complicity.
你明白了吗
Do you understand?
- 我要亲眼看着她被拖去喂狗 - 我们都希望
- I'll see her eaten by dogs. - We may hope.
主啊 泰门来了
Dominus, Timon is here.
泰门 真高兴你能来
Timon, good of you to come.
节哀顺变
I grieve with you.
- 事情糟透了 - 确实是
- Bad business. - It is.
- 你母亲还好吧 对吧？- 她现在不愿见客人
- Your mother's all right, is she? - She's not receiving visitors.
不过她还好 你的人跟你一起来了吗
But she's well enough. Have you men with you?
来了10个 那么她现在还平安 是吗
Ten. So, she's all right, then?
正如我所说的 街上现在状况怎么样
As I said. How's the city?
人们全都闭门不出 到处都是一片死寂
All's indoors. Everywhere's dead quiet.
泰门 感谢你来这儿
Timon, thank you for coming.
看到你我真高兴
I am so happy to see you.
我一听到消息就来了 节哀顺变
I came as soon as I heard. I grieve with you.
你才算得上好朋友 谢谢你
You're a good friend, thank you.
街上现在安全吗 我们现在能离开市区吗
Are the streets safe? Can we get out of the city?
- 现在可以 - 我们应该等一下
- We can. - We should wait a while
三思而后行
before taking any action.
我们对局势并不明了
We do not have a clear view of the position.
- 安东尼也许会 - 如果安东尼还活着 他就该来找我
- Antony may... - If Antony were alive, he would come to me.
至少捎个信
Or send word, at least.
我必须假设安东尼已经死了
I must assume Antony is dead.
这也很有可能 不过我们现在还不知道
It is quite possible, but we cannot know that as yet.
也许他已经逃离了城市
Perhaps he's fled the city.
就这么把我留在这儿 决不可能
And leave me here? Never.
换上赶路的衣服
Put on your traveling clothes.
- 别太显眼的 - 母亲 好好想想
- Nothing fancy. - Mother, think.
你听到赛维莉娅说的话了 她希望你逃掉
You heard what Servilia said. She wants you to run away.
那就再耍耍她 让她来找我好了
More fool her. Let her try and find me.
她肯定会找到你的 你没有躲藏的天赋
She will find you. You have no talent for hiding.
卡斯特拿好钱和家里所有的黄金
Castor, pack the money and the household gods.
现在就去 女主人
Immediately, domina.
跟我来 没时间磨蹭了
Come along, no time to waste.
安东尼
Antony.
我向着黑石起誓 一定会杀光他们所有人
I swear on the black stone that I will kill them all.
布鲁图斯 卡西乌斯 卡斯卡 他们所有人
Brutus and Cassius and Casca and the whole damn lot of them.
他们只不过是赛维莉娅的爪牙 这全是她策划的
They're just Servilia's minions. This is all her doing.
我警告过凯撒
I told Caesar.
我警告过他可能会发生这种事
I told him this would happen.
我发誓 等他们死的时候我要冲他们撒尿
I swear, I will piss on them as they die.
竟然让我 我这样的人东躲西藏
That I should have to run and hide
躲避这些 这些卑微的爬虫
from those... those worms.
你肯定吗 你肯定他已经死了
Are you certain? Are you certain sure he's dead?
喔 当然 他确实已经死了
Oh, yeah. He's dead all right.
我就在那儿 看着他死的
I was there, I saw him.
你就在那儿
You were there?
可你当时怎么没阻止他们
But then why didn't you stop them?
我 我又不是在那儿边上
No, I wasn't there.
我是 他们拖住我 把我挡在阶梯外面
I was... They delayed me outside on the steps.
等我进去之后 一切都已经发生了
By the time I got inside the deed had been done.
他的随从也都跟兔子一样跑得没影了
And the lictors had all run off like rabbits.
那个该死的混帐乌瑞纳斯 他肯定是被收买了
That treacherous bastard Vorenus, he must have been paid off.
他在我们抵达元老院之前就走了
He'd left before we got to the Senate House.
他是被骗走的
He was lured away.
那个妖女赛维莉娅的女佣跟他说了关于他妻子的很不堪的事
The witch Servilia's woman told him an evil tale about his wife.
- 这样啊 你当时在干什么 - 我做了什么
- What did you do then? - What did I do?
怎么了 我什么也做不了
Why, nothing I could do.
凯撒已经死了 我又是赤手空拳
Caesar was dead. I was unarmed.
要是我 就凭双手把他们撕成碎片
Well, I would have ripped them to pieces with my bare hands.
你说得倒轻巧
That's easy for you to say.
你对打斗一窍不通
You know nothing of violence.
只要12只下等的狗就能杀死一头狮子
12 mangy dogs can kill a lion.
好吧 如果你那么说的话
Well, if you say so.
我们现在该干什么
What shall we do now?
你爱干什么干什么
You can do as you like.
我要去北方 组织起一支恐怖的军队
I will go north and raise an army of monsters.
那时我会再回来这里
Then I will come back here
我要把所有这些狗娘养的钉死在十字架上
and I will crucify every last one of those sons of bitches.
你说"你爱干什么干什么"是什么意思
What do you mean, I may do as I like?
如果我想干什么就干什么 那要你来这儿干吗
Why are you here if I may do as I like?
我没什么意思 我当然想你跟我一起走
I meant nothing. Of course I want you to come with me.
得了吧 如果你是要带别的相好走 我就不反对了
Please, if you'd rather take some other lover, I will not protest.
唉 我只是说
No, I meant only that...
我又不能强迫你跟我走
That I cannot force you to come with me.
我猜的话 刚才的那几个小时 你一定是去那些地方了
That's where you were these last hours, I suppose?
把你养的贱女人们藏进车队里去
Putting your whores into... into baggage carts.
我现在没兴趣跟你吵架
I have no stomach for a fight with you.
现在别闹 嗯
Not now, eh?
我不想去北方
I don't want to go north.
北方太吓人了
The north is ghastly.
- 再说一遍你叫什么名字 - 泰门
- What's your name again? - Timon.
泰门 我们准备去北方 你跟你的手下要保护好这家人
We're going north. You and your men will protect the family
直到我能够把我所有的人都集结起来
until I can gather my own people together.
- 收费可不便宜 - 那当然
- It'll cost you. - Of course.
我可不指望犹太人会做义工
I expect no public service from a Jew.
我们得把卡尔普蕊娜一起带走 所以得经过苏布拉
We shall be taking Calpurnia with us, so we must leave via the Subura.
卡尔普蕊娜
Calpurnia?
可为什么我们要带上她
But why do we need to take her?
我们必须保证她的安全
We must be sure that she is safe.
哼 我可没见她急着来问我们是不是安全
Well, I don't see her rushing to see that we're safe.
亲爱的 我们不能把凯撒的遗孀留下
My dear, we cannot leave Caesar's widow behind.
那会让给人们留下不好的印象 就如同我们抛弃了她一样
It would look ill with the people, as if we'd abandoned her.
真烦人
What a bore.
神父
Father.
神父 点醒我吧
Father, wake me.
- 安静 - 点醒我
- Hush. - Wake me.
现在安静 冷静下来
Hush now, be calm.
我会点醒你的 如果你现在放手的话
I will wake you if you will let me go.
答应我
Promise me.
我向火神起誓 我保证
On the fire of Vesta, I promise.
美极了
Lovely.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道我们俩的开局并不怎么好
I know I didn't get us started off on the right foot...
我杀了你的男人还有 我对此很抱歉
Killing your man and all, and I'm sorry for that.
但是 呼 我就跟你直说了吧 我有个问题要问你
But, va, I'll just come straight out with it. I have a question.
经过美神和战神允许
With permission of Venus and Mars...
我请求你做我妻子
I ask you to be my wife.
你妻子 跟你结婚
Your wife? Married?
结婚 就你跟我
Married. You and me.
要 要是你这么希望的话 主人
If... If you wish it so, master.
不不不 我不再是你的主人了 你已经是个自由民了
No, I'm not your master anymore. You're a free woman.
你可以拒绝我 我不会生气的
You can refuse me, I won't be angry.
当然 我也不会很高兴 但是你明白
Well, I won't be best pleased, but you know,
我绝不会为此打你或什么的
I won't beat you or anything.
像我这样的男人总能赚到很多钱
A man like me can always make good money.
你可以住大房子 吃好吃的
You'll have a roof over your head, food.
我会给你买你想要的一切 衣服鞋子之类的
I'll buy you anything you want, dresses, shoes.
这算是同意了
Is that a yes?
是的
Yes.
你一定不会后悔的 我保证
You won't regret it, I promise.
好了
Done.
谢谢你 亲爱的
Thank you, my dear.
有客到 女主人
Visitors, domina.
带他们进来
Bring them.
马克·安东尼 阿提娅
Mark Antony, Atia.
你和孩子们能来真是太好了
How good of you to come, and the children.
卡尔普蕊娜 节哀顺变
Calpurnia, we grieve with you.
知道你能来 我丈夫会很高兴的
My husband is glad to receive you.
你是头一个来致哀的 真奇怪 我们的朋友和亲戚没有一个人来
You're the first to pay respects. None of our friends or family have come.
他们都害怕了
They're afraid.
是的 可能是吧
Ah, yes, that may be so.
我们现在要离开这个城市了
We are going to leave the city now.
你最好也跟我们一起走
It's best you come with us.
离开 为什么
Leaving? Why?
这儿不安全
It is not safe.
没关系 我会乐于迎接死亡
Well, that's no matter. I'm glad to die.
我尊贵的女士
My dear lady...
现在有你在这儿作证 我们可以宣读他的遗嘱了
But now that you're here to stand witness, we must read his will.
他的遗嘱
His will?
对不起 我们可没这个时间
No, I'm sorry. We haven't time.
- 这是必要的形式 - 我们没时间
- It is the proper form. - We haven't time.
这份遗嘱
It is the will...
来自于罗马共和国的独裁者
of a dictator of the Roman Republic.
在确信保留了足够的安居乐业之用
Having made due provision for the well-being and security
给我忠实尽责的妻子卡尔普蕊娜之后
of my honest and dutiful wife, Calpurnia, et cetera,
我将分给每位已登记的公民75便士
I leave the sum of 75 denarii to every enrolled citizen...
哦 真是荒唐 太浪费了
Ridiculous. What a waste.
我的名字和其余的不动产
My name and the remainder of my estate
所有法定的债权与债务
with all legal obligations and benefits,
所有财物与黄金
all property, gold,
银币与其它货币
silver and other monies,
我都留给盖乌斯·屋大维
I leave to Gaius Octavian,
从此以后他将会被视为
who is henceforth to be regarded
我法定的儿子
for all intents and purposes as my lawful son
唯一的继承人
and sole heir.
屋大维 我的屋大维
Octavian? My Octavian?
还有什么？
What else?
他规定叫做伯斯卡的奴隶
He stipulates that the slave known as Posca...
就是我 将被赋予自由
that is I... am to be given my liberty
以及一份适当的津贴
with an appropriate stipend.
我赋予你享受你自由的权利
I give you joy of your freedom.
还有什么
What else?
没有其它要求了
There are no further bequests.
我知道了
I see.
那么 恭喜了 孩子
Well, congratulations, boy.
谢谢你 伯斯卡
Thank you, Posca.
屋大维得到全部一切 所有的
Octavian gets everything? All of it?
他什么也得不到 全都是空头支票
He'll get nothing. It's all wax for scraping.
这是一份遗嘱 这是 他依法拟定的遗嘱
It's a will. It's his by law.
现在布鲁图斯和他的爪牙就是法律
The law is now Brutus and his minions.
凯撒的土地和钱财会落入他们手中
Caesar's land and money will go to them.
就是这样 他们会把他的死 说成是合理的讨伐暴君的行为
That is so. They will declare his death a rightful tyrannicide,
他的遗嘱和所有法令都变得毫无效力
his will and all his acts become null and void,
他的财产会被充公
his property will be intestate.
- 他们不能夺去我的名字 - 当然不
- They cannot take the name. - Oh, no.
那还是你的
That's all yours.
希望能给你带来好运
Much good may it do you.
现在走吧
Away now.
我可能需要强行把卡尔普蕊娜带走
I may have to take Calpurnia along by force,
如果她叫嚷起来的话 别惊慌
so don't be alarmed if she makes a clamor.
嘿 去找你的女主人 告诉她我们要走了
Hey, send for your mistress. Tell her we're leaving.
母亲 我必须留在罗马
Mother, I must stay in Rome.
- 啊 - 我必须留在罗马
- Eh? - I must stay in Rome.
我是凯撒的儿子 我必须捍卫自己的身份与权利
I am Caesar's son. I must protect my status and rights.
真有血性 好一个斯巴达勇士
There's blood. A proper little Spartan.
母亲 你也应该留下
You shall have to stay also, Mother.
整个家应当团结一致
The family must appear united.
我那古怪 勇敢 好高骛远的孩子 我们还是去北方吧
Oh, my strange, brave, pompous little boy, we're going north.
我是一家之主
I'm head of the family.
严格来讲 应该由我决定我们去哪儿
Strictly speaking, it is for me to say where we go.
我知道你想充男子汉 那很可爱
I know you're only trying to be manly and that's lovely.
不过现在时机不对 我们一定要去北方 就这么定了
But now is not the time. We are going and there's an end on it.
安东尼 听我说 布鲁图斯处于一个法律上两难的困境
Antony, listen. Brutus is in a legal bind.
我认为可以强迫他跟我们定一个协议
I think we can force him into making a deal with us.
继续说
Go on.
布鲁图斯必须宣称凯撒是暴君 否则杀害凯撒就算是谋杀
Brutus must declare Caesar a tyrant, else the act of killing Caesar is murder.
然而暴君的所有法令都是不合法的
But all the acts of a tyrant are unlawful,
包括那些指定布鲁图斯作为执政官
Including those appointing Brutus as Praetor,
卡西乌斯当地方总督的法令
Cassius as Proconsul,
- 诸如此类 - 然后呢
- and so forth. - And then so?
如果布鲁图斯遵从法令
If Brutus honors the law,
他将失去所有头衔和地位
he loses all rank and position.
这只是法学家的夸夸其谈
It's lawyers' prattle.
我不这么认为 如果你向他们提供一个特赦
I don't think so. If you offer them amnesty
- 作为回报 - 特赦
- in return... - Amnesty?
我要生吃了他们的肝 还特赦
I'm gonna eat their livers. Amnesty?
你没听懂我的意思
You're not following me.
够了 你以为你比安东尼懂得还多
Enough! You think you know better than Antony?
- 你不明白 - 混蛋 非让我扇你一耳光吗
- But you don't understand. - Juno's cunt, must I slap you?
如果遗嘱生效 而且它肯定会
If the will stands, and it might,
你就是全罗马最富有的母亲了
you are mother to the richest man in Rome.
如果遗嘱被废 赛维莉娅就得到了这份殊荣
If the will is broken, Servilia has that honor.
不行
No.
那该死的女人在哪儿
Where is this damn woman?
当我冲你点头的时候 我要你帮忙抓住那老女人
When I give you the nod, I want you to help me seize the old lady
快点把她带到外面去 她很信任你 是吧
and get her outside quick. She trusts you, nay?
- 阁下 怀着无比敬意 - 什么
- Sir, with all respect... - What?
怀着无比敬意 直到遗嘱被认可前
With all respect, until the will is ratified,
我都必须服侍凯撒一家人 基于这一点
I am bound to serve the house of Caesar.
我必须请求您不要强行带走我的女主人
With that in mind, I must beg you not to take my mistress by force.
- 怀着无比敬意 - 还敬意
- With all respect. - Respect?
你这无耻的蛤蟆
You impudent toad.
你要照我说的做 我高兴怎么对你该死的女主人都行
You'll do as I say, and I will do as I please with your damn mistress.
安东尼
Antony?
我们不走了
We're staying.
不用了 谢谢你 主人
No, thank you, master.
你不要再那么叫我了
You've got to stop calling me that.
那我该叫你什么 随你喜欢
What shall I call you, then?
丈夫或者亲爱的
Anything you want. Husband? Honey?
凯撒死了 凯撒死了
Caesar is dead! Caesar is dead!
凯撒死了
Caesar is dead.
Caesar is dead!
别担心
Don't worry.
该回来的总会回来
If he comes back, he comes back.
好了
There.
看她多漂亮
See how fine she looks?
她会受到尊敬的
She'll be well respected.
一个出身良好的女人
A woman from good people.
你们好啊 孩子们
Hello, children.
不朽功绩
Immortals!
不朽功绩 我要说
Immortals, I say.
你们的名字将被深深地刻在
You noblemen have carved your names
永生石上
deep in the eternal stone.
很高的赞誉
That is very high praise indeed.
我本想拥抱你们 但我太失望了
I would embrace you all but I'm desolated
你们竟然没有把我 列为这场英雄壮举中的一员
that you did not enlist me in your cohort of heroes.
为自由而举刀
To wield the liberators' knife...
使我不能得到你们所获得的快乐
what joy you have denied me.
原谅我们
Forgive us.
不过我们觉得你希望还是不要知道好
But we rather thought you'd prefer not to know.
事已成了
It is done.
我无法分享你们的荣耀
I cannot share in your glory.
我只有为你们鼓掌了
I can only applaud.
告诉我 罗马城安全吗
Now tell me, is the city secure?
我们有2000名全副武装的战士
We have 2,000 men under arms.
- 凯撒的人都四散逃了 - 罗马是我们的了
- Caesar's people have fled. - The city is ours.
好极了 走狗马克·安东尼 我想也死了吧
Excellent, and Mark Antony? The dog is dead I hope?
- 他没死 - 马克·安东尼还活着
- He is not. - Mark Antony is alive?
这是个错误
An error!
很大的错误 我认为
I think, a deep error.
我们是元老院成员 不是暴徒
We are senators, not hired thugs.
你要想他死自己动手吧
Kill him yourself if you want it so.
当然你们最清楚该做什么
Well, well, you know best what is the right thing to do.
我必须走了 去乡下
I must go. I'm away to the country.
有一场无聊的诉讼案等我 我只想在走之前表示对你们的敬意
Another tedious lawsuit. I just wanted to salute you before I left.
伟大的解放者
Immortal liberators.
西赛罗 我的朋友
Friend Cicero.
你脸色不太好啊
Why so pale?
兄弟
Brother?
乌瑞纳斯
Vorenus?
- 士兵波罗 一排 二岗 - 出什么事了
- Legionary Pullo, Second Century... - What's happened?
一排
...First Cohort, First Cohort.
乌瑞纳斯兄弟 出什么事了
Brother Vorenus, what's happened?
她是小卢西尔斯的生母
She's mother to the boy Lucius.
我想… 杀了她
I was... going to kill her.
我拿着刀
I had the knife in my hand.
她自己解决了
She did it herself.
太可怕了
Miseria.
- 孩子们在哪儿 - 走了
- Where are the children? - Gone.
去哪儿了
Gone where?
我诅咒了他们
I cursed them.
我诅咒他们下阴间
I cursed them to Hades.
去拿点水
Get some water.
乌瑞纳斯兄弟
Brother Vorenus.
- 乌瑞纳斯兄弟 - 什么
- Brother Vorenus. - What
过来坐下
Come sit down.
先洗洗干净怎么样
Let's get you cleaned up.
执政官安东尼 我来这儿 是来表达我作为中立仲裁者的立场
Consul Antony, I am here strictly as an impartial arbiter.
我对这场混乱一无所知
I knew nothing of this disturbing act.
我和你一样感到意外和震惊
I was as surprised and... and shocked as you were.
布鲁图斯可以为我作证
As Brutus can confirm.
对 西赛罗什么都不知道
Cicero knew nothing.
今天你失去了一个挚友和保护者
You have lost a good friend and patron today.
我们很抱歉
We are sorry.
如果再让我看到那个小丑 我要亲自割了他的喉咙
If that monkey remains I shall have to open his neck.
今天早晨他差点杀了我 他在这儿是对我的侮辱
He tried to kill me this morning. His presence is an insult.
你误会了 没人打算杀你
You're mistaken. No one tried to kill you.
我下了命令不能伤害你
It was my express order that you be spared.
是吗 卡西乌斯 是我误会了
Am I, Cassius? Mistaken?
如果这个人有过激行为 我们表示道歉
We do apologize if this man's been overzealous.
出去 昆特斯
Go, Quintus.
说吧 安东尼
Tell us, Antony...
什么风把你吹到这儿来了
to what do we owe this unexpected pleasure?
听
Listen.
为什么这么平静
Why so quiet?
一个暴君死了
A tyrant is dead.
人民理应高兴
Surely the people should be happy.
欢呼声在哪儿
Where is the cheering throng at your door?
获得自由后高兴的哭喊在哪儿
Where are the joyous cries of liberty?
人民害怕改变
The people fear change.
不知所措是正常的
A somber mood is only... natural.
一旦他们意识到从此摆脱了暴政
When they realize they are free from tyranny,
他们会高兴的
the people will be glad.
人民爱凯撒
The people loved Caesar.
他们会因为你的所作所为而恨你
And they will hate you for what you've done.
他们曾经很爱他 我也一样
They loved him once. As I did.
毫无疑问有人开始反对他
Some have turned against him, no doubt.
不能否认他是个暴君
It cannot be denied he was something of a tyrant.
但还是会有一大批人 到死都把凯撒当神一样膜拜
But a great many people will worship Caesar until they die.
一大批人
A great many.
而那些人现在都站在我这边了
And those people are mine now.
我们不需要这些人 我们的武装士兵会保护城市
We do not need such people. Our men-at-arms have secured the city.
我们取得了所有有利方的支持 元老支持我们 圣骑士支持我们
We've received representatives from the best elements. The Senate is with us, the knights.
还有大祭司 城市军团 侍从官
The pontiffs, the urban cohorts, the lictors' guild.
侍从官 太好了
Oh, the lictors' guild, very good.
再召集面包师和吹长笛的
Only rally the bakers and the flute-players,
你们就能开个庆功宴了
and you can put on a festival.
不过最好是等大选之后
Best wait till after the elections, though.
什么大选
What elections?
你们不会没想过吧
Surely you've thought this through.
如果你们坚持说凯撒是个暴君
If Caesar was, as you insist, a tyrant,
那他所有的法例和任命都是无效的
then all his acts and appointments are nullified.
我不再是执政官
I am no longer consul,
你不再是司法官 你也不再是副执政
you're no longer praetor, you're no longer proconsul.
必须重新选举
Elections will have to be held.
确实如此
That is so.
要是重选 事情可不妙了
Messy things, elections.
你说过会帮我们
You spoke of helping us?
没错
I did.
所有热爱凯撒但痛恨暴政的人
All those that loved Caesar, but hate tyranny...
我有办法让他们站在你们这边
I may be able to bring to your side.
你为什么要这么做
Why would you do that?
没有人能彻底胜利
Neither of us can win outright.
斗争没有不流血的
Not without much blood spilled to prove the issue.
我不想再有流血了
I want no more blood.
我想要和平 和稳定
I want peace and stability.
要怎么做
How?
首先 大赦全国
First, a general amnesty.
不要对外宣称凯撒是暴君 你们也不会被宣称为弑君者
Caesar is not declared tyrant, nor you declared killers.
凯撒的法律和遗嘱 仍然成立
All Caesar's acts, and his will, shall stand.
我们都保持原职
We shall all keep our posts.
必须搞得像他遭了雷击一样
It will be as if he were struck by lightning.
自然死亡
A natural death.
说下去
Go on.
然后要展示给公众看我们仍然团结 为凯撒举行公开葬礼
Then a show of unity. A public funeral for Caesar,
你和我一起主持
led by you and I together.
我们要埋葬暴君为他哀悼
We shall mourn the man and burn the tyrant.
接着我就继续做我的执政官
And then?
直到任期结束
I shall serve out the rest of my term as consul,
然后我退居行省
and then retire quietly to the provinces
每天种种地
where I will plough my fields
干几个仆人
and fuck my slaves.
就像老辛辛纳图斯一样
Just like old Cincinnatus.
共和将永存 但与我无关了
And the Republic shall roll on without me.
我向黑石发誓
I swear on the black stone,
我受够政治了
I am done with politics.
哦 你的人也太狠了
You people play too rough
对于我这样一个纯粹的战士来说
for a simple soldier like me.
在元老院里动刀
Knives in the Senate House?
没想到你还是这块料
Didn't think you had it in you.
如果我们不接受你的提议呢
And if we do not wish to be reconciled with you?
非友即敌
Well, if we cannot be friends, then we shall be enemies.
我会竭尽所能把你们全部消灭
And I will do my very best to annihilate you.
能否给我们一些时间商量商量
Perhaps you would give us some time to talk this over?
尽管商量吧
You can talk all you like.
我在外面等
I shall wait outside.
是你下命令杀他吗 你忘了我说的
You tried to kill him despite everything I said?
原谅我
Forgive me.
你有你的顾虑 但是你如果不知情
Your scruples do you credit, but without your knowledge
他死了不会伤害到你的荣誉
his death could not have dishonored you...
相反 我会罪加一等
To the contrary, I will be twice dishonored.
一个轼君者加傻瓜
A killer and a fool.
你个人荣誉比共和国更重要吗
Is your honor worth more than the Republic?
还不晚
It is not too late.
他就在这儿 在你们手里
He's here, in your hands.
我只是在陈述事实
I'm simply stating the facts.
我可没有强迫你采取什么行动
I do not urge you to any particular course of action.
你所谓没有强迫我的事我不会做的
Nor will I take the course you do not urge.
兄弟
Brother.
这是唯一理智的做法
It is the only rational thing to do.
他没有违反法律
He's broken no capital law.
他提出了休战 这样可以维持共和国的秩序
And he offers a truce which will preserve the public order.
- 我们没有权利杀他 - 去他的法律吧 他活着是威胁
- We have no right to take his life. - Damn the law! He's too dangerous to live.
你高看他了 他只是个下流的禽兽
You exaggerate him. He is a vulgar beast.
没有了凯撒他很快就会自毁前程
Without Caesar he will destroy himself soon enough.
- 他是 - 他是我家里的客人
- He is... - He is a guest in my house.
他不在家里 他在大街上
He is not in the house. He is on the street.
你也这么认为 母亲
You too, Mother?
执政官安东尼
Consul Antony...
我们休战
we shall be friends.
朋友
Friends, eh?
天哪
My god.
好了 这样好多了
There. That's better.
- 我不该那么做 - 做什么
- I shouldn't have done it. - What's that?
我诅咒了自己的孩子 波罗
I cursed my own children, Pullo.
那不是他们的错
It wasn't their fault.
别担心 他们会回来的
Don't worry, they'll be back.
然后你可以解除诅咒 没问题的 你没有杀牛宰羊吧
You can lift the curse then, no trouble. You didn't kill an animal on it, did you?
- 没有 - 那就没问题了
- No. - There you go, then.
诅咒没有生效
The curse isn't sealed.
等他们回来了 你就能解除了 不会有伤害
And when they come back, you can lift it. No harm done.
如果他们不回来呢
What if they don't come back?
那还能去哪儿 他们当然会回来
Where else they gonna go? Course they're coming back.
明天凌晨四点
Tomorrow, at the fourth hour,
有一场公开葬礼 死者是盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
a funeral service will be held for Gaius Julius Caesar.
本着诚实 团结和宽容的精神
Under terms of truth and in the spirit of unity and forgiveness,
将有一场演讲
eulogies will be delivered
演讲者是司法官 马克·朱尼斯·布鲁图斯
by Praetor Marcus Junius Brutus
以及执政官马克·安东尼
and Consul Mark Antony.
卖淫者 演员
No prostitutes, actors
做小买卖的 不得参加
or unclean tradesmen may attend.
我来悼念你的丈夫
I am come to pay my respects to your husband.
我理解你心存怨恨
I understand you are grieving.
带她去看她做的好事
Show her what she's done.
所以乌瑞纳斯回家和他妻子对质
So Vorenus went home to confront his wife
凯撒一个人 在没有保护的情况下去了元老院
and Caesar went to the Senate alone and unprotected.
混蛋
Bastards.
但我不明白的是
What I don't understand
他们怎么知道内奥比的事
is how they knew about Niobe and all that in the first place.
只有你和我知道事情真相
You and I were the only ones that knew the truth.
我告诉了我姐姐
I told my sister.
她告诉了赛维莉娅
And she told Servilia.
我姐姐她 这不重要
My sister was... It doesn't matter.
事情已经捅破了 再后悔也于事无补了
The jug is broken, I cannot mend it with regret.
我请求你的原谅
I ask for your forgiveness.
我当然不会怪你
Of course.
我没想到你这样的小公子哥会
I can't expect a young lad like yourself to be...
会…
to be...
不管怎么说 就像你说的 事情已经捅破了
Anyway, it's done, as you say.
我对你说的别再告诉别人了
You should not repeat what I have told you.
不是因为羞愧 虽然我确实很羞愧
It's not that I'm ashamed, though I am.
我只是不想破坏自己的公众形象
It's only that it will not look good with the people.
我已经全忘了
It's forgotten already.
对于你叔叔的死我很难过
Sorry about your uncle.
根据遗嘱我是他的继承人
I am made his son by will.
恭喜你
Congratulations?
那么你想报复吗
You'll be wanting vengeance, then?
有点想
At some point.
当然 我会为你效力
I'll be up for the duty, of course.
哦快点 起来
Oh, come on, get up.
你忘了今天什么日子了
Have you forgotten what day it is?
是吗 什么日子
What day is it?
别跟我开玩笑了 我今天没兴趣和你玩
Don't play with me. I'm not up for it today.
放松点
Relax.
今天是我的大日子
It's gonna be my day.
我能感觉到
I can feel it.
我想我还未曾干过穿着丧衣的女人
I don't think I've ever fucked a woman in a funeral dress before.
现在你也别想
Nor shall you now.
太可惜了
That's a shame.
那就让玛如拉来
It'll have to be Merula, then.
过来 老姑娘 跳上来
Come here, old girl. Jump on.
她会生吃了你
She'd eat you alive.
好了 不是干傻事的时候 快起来
Come on, this is no morning for foolery. Just get up.
过来吧
Come here.
别乱来 起来
Stop fooling around and just get up!
我可不起来 除非你找个人来给我干
I am not rising from this bed until I've fucked someone.
好吧好吧 玛如拉 把厨房那个日尔曼贱货叫来
Fine. Merula, fetch that German slut from the kitchen.
快点吧 好好干 不然你就是下一届"公羊之王"的候选人了
Come on, get it right this time or you'll be next for the "King of Goats" over there.
殡仪队来了 该走了
Undertaker's here. We're ready to go.
我们必须等孩子们
We must wait for the children.
他们会回来的 兄弟
They'll be back, brother.
我不该那么做
I shouldn't have done it.
我不该诅咒他们
I shouldn't have cursed them.
他们会回来 我确定 迟早会回来
They'll be back. I'm sure of it. Sooner or later.
我不该这么做 我不该这么做
I shouldn't have done it. I shouldn't have done it.
嘿 嘿
Hei, Hei
嘿
Hei
是时候送内奥比上路了
We've got to send Niobe on her way now.
不能再拖延了 对不对
We can't leave it any longer, can we?
惹恼了死神可不好
Else them below will be vexed.
行行好 行行好
Please. Please.
农政官
Grain monitor?
为什么我要去当什么该死的农政官
Why on Gaia's earth would I want to be grain monitor?
这样你就有理由不失尊严的离开城市了
It would give you reason to leave with dignity.
我不会离开这里
I have no intention of leaving the city.
去一趟亚洲的几个供货港口 是最自然不过的事情了
A tour of the Asian supply ports would be the most natural thing in the world.
没有人会指责你逃走
Nobody could possibly accuse you of running away.
我绝不离开这里
I have no intention of leaving the city!
赛维莉娅 亲爱的
Servilia, my dear...
我很抱歉
Sorry about all this.
你的情绪有点失控了
Got a bit carried away.
你的演讲很精彩
You gave an excellent speech, incidentally.
不过也许有点太深奥了
It was perhaps a touch too cerebral
对于不太有文化的听众来说 但是
for that audience, but...
你要来点什么吗
Have you been offered any refreshment?
来点水就行了
Some water will be lovely.
谢谢
Thank you.
拜托了 和你儿子好好说说
Please, speak sense to your son.
他和他的朋友必须离开城市
Him and his friends must leave the city.
否则我不能确保他们的安全
I cannot answer for their safety.
你别那么得意
Do not look so pleased with yourself.
你是个骗子 你违背了誓言
You're a liar and a breaker of oaths,
你只是唤起了一些暴民 仅此而已
and you've roused your rabble, nothing more.
闹剧演员也能做的雕虫小技
A pantomime actor might have done what you did today.
幸运的是 做的人是我 不是吗
Lucky then it was me that did it, eh?
不然你们现在就得乖乖的 跪在闹剧演员面前吸他的老二了
Else you would now be on your knees sucking pantomime cock.
我不是想嘲笑或者羞辱你们
I have no wish to abuse or humiliate you.
我只是要你们走
I only wish you gone.
我们哪儿也不去
We're going nowhere.
不 至少你不用走
No, not you, at least.
男人们必须离开
The men shall leave.
你可以留在这里 作为我的客人
You will stay here in the city with me as my guest.
- 你的意思是 人质 - 随你怎么说
- Hostage, you mean. - As you like.
你可以一厢情愿
You may wish as you will.
但所有的元老还是支持我们的所有有实权的人
We yet have all the Senate behind us and all the men of quality.
而我有一群愤怒的暴民
And I have an angry mob...
他们会在烧了元老院后
that will roast and eat your "men of quality"
咆哮着吃了你们所谓的"有实权的人"
in the ashes of the Senate House!
孩子们 老大
Children? Eldest?
沃伦娜
Vorena?
他们不在
They're not here.
别担心 耐心点
Never mind. Just have to be patient.
去煮点麦片粥好吗
How about you make us a nice pot of porridge?
吃点东西感觉会好点
We'll all feel better with some food inside us.
- 沃伦娜 - 有人吗
- Vorena? - Anyone here?
对不起 对不起 我只是想拿回我借你们的东西
I'm sorry. I was only taking back things I lent.
别说了 这不重要 你知道孩子们去哪儿了吗
Hush, it doesn't matter. Do you know where the children are run to?
我发誓 我只拿了我借你们的东西
I swear, only things I lent.
你到底知不知道孩子们在哪儿
Do you know where the children are?
说
Speak!
他们被伊拉斯特斯·弗尔曼抓走了
Erastes' foreman took them.
波卡·朱诺
Porca Juno.
我为你难过
I'm very sorry for your loss.
那地方他妈的挤得水泄不通 我花了半小时才挤到最前面
The place is fucking packed, yeah? Takes me half an hour to fight me way to the front
布鲁图斯站在上面
and up steps Brutus.
知道吗
Right?
他说:怎么怎么怎么
And he goes, "Blah, blah, blah.
一会儿这个法 一会儿共和国怎么怎么
"The law this and the Republic that.
"12圆桌骑士怎么怎么"
"And the 12 bloody tables."
大部分我都听不懂
I couldn't understand half of it.
接下去呢
Yeah, yeah, then what happened?
接着 安东尼站了起来 但是他拥抱了布鲁图斯
Then, Antony's up. But he gives Brutus a hug.
他慢慢的温和的说着 好像他一点也不生气
He starts talking all calm and gentle like he's not bothered.
我正在想: 真是一派胡言 还是去找个妞玩玩
And I'm thinking, "Bollocks, we'll be away for a bevvy."
但是突然
But then...
他拿出凯撒的袍子
he pulls out Caesar's toga,
沾满了鲜血
all covered in blood.
大伙儿都吓退了
Everyone goes, "Whoa!"
恶心 那家伙丝毫不懂自尊
Disgusting. No fucking dignity, that man.
安东尼拿着袍子跳上跳下
But now, Antony's stalking up and down with the toga
他哭喊着说:凯撒是多么好的人呐
and he's crying about "What a good man was Caesar"
说他有多爱他 说我们失去了一个伟大的领袖
and how much he loves him and what a great leader we've lost
直说到人群有一半都哭了起来
until the crowd... half of them are crying...
他们像小孩子一样抽泣着
they're sobbing like babies.
然后他干了什么 他拿起那件血袍
And then what does he do? He takes the bloody toga...
扔向了人群 哇
and throws it into the crowd. Whoosh!
整个地方他妈突然沸腾了
The whole fucking place went up like a tar barrel.
人群整个他妈的疯了
The whole fucking crowd went mad.
布鲁图斯他们还能活着算他们走运 如果他们还活着的话
Brutus and them are lucky to be alive. If they are.
太丢脸了 毫无尊严
It's a disgrace. No fucking respect.
- 但是人群确实很愤怒 不是吗 - 别找借口
- Yeah, well people get angry, don't they? - No excuse.
这是给他妈的执政官开葬礼 不是吗
It's a consular fucking funeral, isn't it?
为的是他妈的荣耀他
Supposed to show some fucking respect.
不是屠杀和焚烧
Not run around looting and burning.
禽兽
Animals.
安东尼是个杂种
That Antony's a cunt, too.
给我记住
Mark me, now.
你们里面还有谁要丢自己的脸 就立马给我滚蛋
Any one of you cunnies join in this disgrace, you'll be disjointed quick as Pan.
我们是讲体面的
We observe the fucking decencies.
- 听懂没有 - 懂了
- Right? - Right.
该死的奴隶外邦人
Fucking slaves and foreigners to blame.
把他们全赶回庇推尼或者什么鬼地方
Send them back to Bithynia, or wherever the fuck you come from.
罗马是属于他妈的罗马人的
Rome for fucking Romans, eh?
弗拉维奥
Flavio?
叫那些杂种闭嘴
Tell those damn scurras to shut that up!
要打出去打
They want to fight, take it outside.
把手放上去
Keep your hands above it!
弗拉维奥
Flavio!
真他妈没用
Fucking useless.
你抓了我的孩子们
You have my children.
你他妈说什么呢
Eh? What the fuck you talking about?
你抓了我的孩子们
You have my children.
你被骗了 朋友
Someone's misled you, friend.
他们在哪儿
Where are they?
我不知道
I don't know.
他们在哪儿
Where are they?
弗拉维奥
Flavio!
弗拉维奥不会来了
Flavio's not coming.
都到齐了
Here we are, then.
他们在哪儿
Where are they?
我的孩子在哪儿
Where are my children?
要来点酒吗
Will you have a little wine with me?
不要 好吧
No? Well...
亲我屁股吧
kiss my arse.
说出来
Tell him.
如果他们没有受到伤害 我们也许不会杀你
If they're not harmed, you may yet live.
是吗
You think so?
说吧
Tell him.
没什么酒能和费乐纳斯酒媲美 是不是
Nothing like a good Falernian grape, is there?
你人不坏 乌瑞纳斯
You're not a bad sort of man, Vorenus.
你只是气疯头了
You just have too much anger in you.
告诉他
Tell him!
我抓你的孩子是对你轻视我的报复
I took your children in payment for your many slights to me.
先奸 后杀
I fucked them, then I killed them.
最后把他们扔进河里
And then I threw them in the river.